Malavika Samak

Massachusetts Institute of Technology G740, 32 Vassar St, Cambridge, MA 02139 malavika@csail.mit.edu www.malavikasamak.com

My research aims to develop techniques, tools, and workflows to improve developer productivity and software quality by enabling developers to **discover**, **analyze**, **customize**, **and adapt code**. I proposed the first set of algorithms that automatically **synthesize targeted tests** to reveal thread-safety violations in classes. I have also proposed algorithms for safely replacing classes by synthesizing **verified adapters**. Currently, I am exploring **functionality-based search techniques** to identify relevant classes from large code corpora.

tags: program analysis, concurrency, test generation, program synthesis, code search, object-oriented programming

WORK EXPERIENCE

CSAIL, MIT, Cambridge, USA Postdoctoral Associate	2017 - Present
Microsoft Research, Bangalore, India Visiting Researcher	2017
Google, Mountain View, USA Software Engineering Intern	2016
NDS - Cisco , Bangalore, India Software Engineer	2010 - 2012

EDUCATION

Indian Institute of Science (IISc), Bangalore, India Ph.D. in Computer Science Thesis: Targeted Client Synthesis for Detecting Concurrency Bugs	2012 - 2017
Sri Jayachamarajendra College of Engineering , Mysore, India B.E. in Computer Science and Engineering	2006 - 2010

PUBLICATIONS

Summary: Published 9 peer-reviewed papers: 7 conference papers and 2 tool/demo papers, in the following venues – POPL, SOSP, PLDI, OOPSLA, FSE, PPoPP, and SPLASH.

Peer-reviewed Conference Publications

POPL Synthesizing Replacement Classes
Malavika Samak, Deokhwan Kim, and Martin C. Rinard
47th ACM SIGPLAN Symposium on Principles of Programming Languages,
2020, Acceptance: 27.5% (68/247)

SOSP Optimizing Big-Data Queries Using Program Synthesis

Matthias Schlaipfer, Kaushik Rajan, Akash Lal, and **Malavika Samak** 26th ACM Symposium on Operating Systems Principles, 2017, Acceptance: 16.8% (39/232)

OOPSLA Directed Synthesis of Failing Concurrent Executions

Malavika Samak, Omer Tripp, and Murali Krishna Ramanathan ACM SIGPLAN International Conference on Object-Oriented Programming, Systems, Languages, and Applications, 2016, Acceptance: 25.6% (52/203)

PLDI Synthesizing Racy Tests

Malavika Samak, Murali Krishna Ramanathan, and Suresh Jagannathan ACM SIGPLAN Conference on Programming Language Design and Implementation, 2015, Acceptance: 19.1% (58/303), Artifact Evaluated, Top 10 Video Abstract.

FSE Synthesizing Tests for Detecting Atomicity Violations

Malavika Samak and Murali Krishna Ramanathan

ACM SIGSOFT Symp. on the Foundations of Software Engineering, 2015, Acceptance: 25.4% (74/291), Artifact Evaluated

OOPSLA Multithreaded Test Synthesis for Deadlock Detection

Malavika Samak and Murali Krishna Ramanathan

ACM SIGPLAN International Conference on Object-Oriented Programming, Systems, Languages, and Applications, 2014, Acceptance: 28.6% (53/185), Artifact Evaluated

PPoPP Trace Driven Dynamic Deadlock Detection and Reproduction

Malavika Samak and Murali Krishna Ramanathan

ACM SIGPLAN Symposium on Principles and Practice of Parallel Programming, 2014, Acceptance: 15.6% (28/179)

Tool/Demo Papers

FSE Omen+: A Precise Dynamic Deadlock Detector for Multithreaded Java Libraries

Malavika Samak and Murali Krishna Ramanathan

ACM SIGSOFT Symp. on Foundations of Software Engineering, 2014

SPLASH Omen: A Tool for Synthesizing Tests for Deadlock Detection

Malavika Samak and Murali Krishna Ramanathan

ACM SIGPLAN Conference on Systems, Programming, and Applications: Soft-

ware for Humanity, 2014

Technical Reports

Archive Searching for Replacement Classes

Malavika Samak, Jose Pablo Cambronero, and Martin C. Rinard

Under Submission, 2021

Technical Clearscope: Full Stack Provenance Graph Generation for Transparent Computing

Report on Mobile Devices

Michaell Gordon, Jordan Eikenberry, Anthony Eden, Jeffrey Perkins, **Malavika Samak**, Henny Sipma, and Martin C. Rinard Massachusetts Institute of Technology, Cambridge, United States, 2020

RESEARCH PROJECTS

Synthesizing Verified Adapters

Designed and implemented a system, which receives a pair of Java classes as input and automatically synthesizes an adapter class that implements the same interface as the first input class by using the APIs offered by the second input class. The approach leverages the strengths of symbolic execution, constraint solving, and program synthesis to construct adapter classes.

Synthesizing Multithreaded Tests

Designed and implemented the first set of algorithms that automatically generate targeted multithreaded tests for detecting concurrency bugs in Java libraries. The automatically synthesized tests constructed by the synthesizers helped expose more than 300 concurrency bugs in popular libraries (Oracle Java Development Kit, Google Guava Collections, HyperSQL DataBase, Apache OpenNLP, etc.), including many previously unknown bugs that were subsequently fixed.

Code Search for Java Classes

Designed a new technique and implemented a system, ClassFinder, for automatically finding Java classes. Given a query class, ClassFinder automatically searches large codebases to identify and rank potential classes that can act as a drop-in replacement to the query class by combining two complementary techniques: embedding-based class ranking and method compatibility matching. Evaluation on ≈ 600 thousand open-source classes demonstrates that ClassFinder can effectively find appropriate classes.

Talks

Invited Rising Stars in Computer Science Series, U. Mass. Amherst, 2019 talks Microsoft Research, Bangalore, 2017

Google, Mountain View, 2016

Dagstuhl Seminar on Concurrency (Tutorial), 2016

DRDO-IISc workshop on verification of System Software, IISc, 2016

Hewlett Packard Enterprise, Bangalore, 2015 Undergraduate Summer School, IISc, 2014

Conference talks

POPL: Synthesizing Replacement Classes, 2020

OOPSLA: Directed Synthesis of Failing Concurrent Executions, 2016 **FSE**: Synthesizing Tests for Detecting Atomicity Violations, 2015

PLDI: Synthesizing Racy Tests, 2015

OOPSLA: Multithreaded Test Synthesis for Deadlock Detection, 2014 PPoPP: Trace Driven Deadlock Detection and Reproduction, 2014

AWARDS AND HONORS

- Invited speaker for Rising Stars in Computer Science Seminar, University of Massachusetts, Amherst, 2019.
- Invited to attend the 4th Heidelberg Laureate Forum, 2016.
- Invited to the **Dagstuhl Seminar** on concurrency, 2016.
- Received Google Ph.D. fellowship, 2015.
- PLDI video abstract voted in the Top 10 by the attendees, 2015.
- Invited to speak at Google Test Automation Conference, 2015
- Secured All India Rank 107 (out of 156,780 candidates) in Graduate Aptitude Test Entrance (GATE), 2012.
- President Award for Girl Scouts, Government of India, 2004.

TEACHING, GRANTS, AND MENTORSHIP

- Co-organized the Programming Languages Mentoring Workshop (PLMW) at SPLASH 2020. The event received over 120 student applications that included 40 women applicants.
- Presented in AMP-DARPA engagement and contributed to HACCS and SafeDocs DARPA grant proposals.
- Teaching assistant for the graduate-level course on Operating Systems, IISc.
- Guest lecturer for the graduate-level course on Software Engineering, IISc.
- Mentored four undergraduate summer interns between 2014-16. They subsequently joined graduate programs at Carnegie Mellon University and Stanford University.
- Co-organized Technologix 2009, a three-day national-level computer science symposium conducted by the Computer Society of India, SJCE.

SERVICE

Co-chair PLMW: Programming Languages Mentoring Workshop, SPLASH 2020

AEC: Artifact Evaluation Committee, PPoPP 2018

Program Committee

PLDI: Programming Languages, Design and Implementation, 2022

ittee SC: Super Computing, 2021

ICCQ: International Conference on Code Quality, 2021 ICPP: International Conference on Parallel Processing, 2020

SC: Super Computing, 2019

PPoPP: Principles and Practices of Parallel Programming, 2019

OOPSLA: Object Oriented Programming, Systems, Languages, and Applica-

tions, 2018

Journal TOPLAS: Transactions on Programming Languages and Systems, 2021

Reviewer TSE: Transactions on Software Engineering, 2019

External OOPSLA: Object Oriented Programming, Systems, Languages, and Applica-

Program tions, 2019

Committee PPoPP: Principles and Practices of Parallel Programming, 2018

Reviewer SRC, Student Research Competition, SPLASH 2021

SRC, Student Research Competition, PLDI 2018

Artifact PLDI: Programming Languages Design and Implementation, 2017

Evaluation PPoPP: Principles and Practices of Parallel Programming, 2017

PLDI: Programming Languages Design and Implementation, 2016

OOPSLA: Object Oriented Programming, Systems, Languages, and Applica-

tions, 2016

PPoPP: Principles and Practices of Parallel Programming, 2016

POPL: Principles of Programming Languages, 2016

OOPSLA: Object Oriented Programming, Systems, Languages, and Applica-

tions, 2015

REFERENCES

Martin C. Rinard

Professor, Department of EECS Massachusetts Institute of Technology

rinard@csail.mit.edu

Suresh Jagannathan

Professor, Department of Computer Science

Purdue University suresh@cs.purdue.edu

Sriram Rajamani

Distinguished Scientist & Managing Director

Microsoft Research India sriram@microsoft.com

Xiangyu Zhang

Professor, Department of Computer Science

Purdue University xyzhang@cs.purdue.edu

Patrick Eugster

Professor, Computer Systems Institute Università della Svizzera Italiana (USI)

eugstp@usi.ch

Omer Tripp

Senior Applied Scientist

Amazon Science

omertrip@amazon.com